Guide to the Josephine Boardman Crane Papers Relating to the Dalton School
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Josephine Boardman Crane papers relating to the Dalton School
1915-1972
1915-1930
YCAL MSS 1002
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.92
(5 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, notes, photographs and printed material relating to Josephine Boardman Crane, Helen Parkhurst, the Dalton School, and to progressive education in the United States during the 1920s.
Crane, Josephine Boardman, 1873-1972
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, reports, notes, photographs and printed material relating to Josephine Boardman Crane, Helen Parkhurst, the Dalton School, the Dalton Laboratory Plan, and to progressive education in the United States during the 1920s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josie Green, 1994.
Josephine Boardman Crane (1873-1972)
Josephine Porter Boardman Crane was born in Cleveland, Ohio, November 1, 1873, daughter of William Jarvis and Florence Sheffield Boardman. In 1906 she married U.S. Senator Winthrop Murray Crane, and they lived in Washington, D.C., until his retirement from the Senate in 1913. Crane took an active role in furthering children's welfare, establishing a School for Crippled Children in Pittsfield, Massachusetts, the Dalton Visiting Nurse Service, and working to improve conditions for children in the Crane paper mills at Dalton, Massachusetts. Through her collaboration with educator Helen Parkhurst, Crane became a leading figure in promoting progressive education methods, founding the Dalton School in New York City in 1920. Crane served as a trustee of the Dalton School, the Berkshire Museum in Pittsfield, the Museum of Modern Art in New York City, the Pierpont Morgan Library, the American Opera Society, and the China Institute in America, among many other institutions. In 1971 she authored a memoir of her childhood, A Middle-West Child (New York: Spiral Press). Crane died in Falmouth, Massachusetts on July 8, 1972.
Dalton laboratory plan; Educators -- United States -- Archives; Philanthropists -- United States; Progressive education -- United States; Women philanthropists -- United States; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Educators -- United States -- 20th Century; Crane, Josephine Boardman, 1873-1972; Parkhurst, Helen, 1887-1973; Dalton School (New York, N.Y.)
- Grades 4-8 assignments, 1920s; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Louise Crane assignments, 1920s; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Assignment cards and report cards, undated (Box 1)
- Assignments, undated (Box 1)
- Children's University School, printed material, 1924-1926 (Box 1)
- "History - The Dalton Plan," by Miss Helen Parkhurst, 1930 July (Box 1)
- Reports and articles on the Dalton Laboratory Plan, 1922-1930 (Box 1)
- Teachers' statements and clippings relating to Dalton High School, 1920-1928 (Box 1)
- An outline of the Dalton Plan in China, by Milton S. C. Hsu, 1924 April (Box 1)
- Pamphlets and articles on education, 1917-1925 (Box 1)
- Reports and publications relating to progressive education in Europe, 1923-1927 (Box 2)
- Reports and publications relating to education in England and the Dalton Plan, 1921-1924; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Japanese arithmetic assignment, undated (Box 2)
- Five lectures on the Dalton Plan given in Japan by Helen Parkhurst, typescripts, 1924 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and other material relating to Helen Parkhurst's trip to Japan and China, 1924-1925 (Box 2)
- "Illustrated mathematical talks by pupils of the Lincoln school," pamphlet, circa 1919 (Box 2)
- Correspondence relating to the Ohio State University Experimental School, 1927 (Box 2)
- Photographs of work by the pupils at the Dalton Schools, New York, 1920s (Box 2)
- Helen Parkhurst correspondence, 1927 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and printed material relating to Pleasantville, New York, 1923 (Box 2)
- "Pedagogy at Moscow and Russian-American educational cooperation," by Peter Tutyshkin, 1924 (Box 2)
- Printed material relating to San Francisco State Normal School, 1915-1917 (Box 2)
- Correspondence and clippings relating to Scarsdale, New York, 1923 (Box 3)
- Correspondence relating to West Virginia University Demonstration School, 1925 (Box 3)
- Printed material relating to Winnetka, Illinois, 1920 (Box 3)
- Bibliography of the Dalton Plan, 1927 November (Box 3)
- "Does preparation for college prepare children for life," by Mrs. M. Murray Crane, 1928 (Box 3)
- Dalton School Committee correspondence, 1920 (Box 3)
- Obituaries of Josephine Porter Boardman Crane and Helen Parkhurst, 1972, undated (Box 3)
- Letter from Michael Sadler, University of Leeds, to Josephine Crane, 1923 (Box 3)
- "A concrete report to the education committee of the Berkshire School for Crippled Children", 1919 October 1 (Box 3)
- Josephine Crane correspondence relating to the Dalton Plan, 1923 (Box 3)
- Lectures by Maria Montessori at the Montessori Normal College, New York City, transcripts, 1916 (Box 3)
- Letters from Helen Parkhurst to Josephine Crane, 1921-1925; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Postcards from Helen Parkhurst to Crane family members, 1920 (Box 3)
- Helen Parkhurst papers relating to the Children's University School, 1922 (Box 3)
- Notes and reports relating to the Laboratory School and the Dalton Plan, 1920 (Box 3)
- "Notes for talk given to Dalton School trustees by Josephine Boardman Crane", 1953 May 19 (Box 3)
- Reprints of articles by C. Macfie Campbell, 1919-1920 (Box 3)
- "A series of articles on education," by Aldous Huxley, reprinted from Vanity Fair, 1926 (Box 3)
- Reprints of articles by Maria Montessori, 1915-1916 (Box 3)
- Clippings, 1921-1929 (Box 3)
- Unsorted papers, 1923-1926 (Box 4)
- "Report of the tenth annual conference of educational associations, held at the University College, London", 1922 (Box 4)
- "Report of the eleventh annual conference of educational associations, held at the University College, London", 1923 (Box 4)
- "American boarding schools," by Horace D. Taft, 1913 (Box 4)
- Letters to Josephine Crane, 1921 (Box 4)
- Printed material relating to education, 1917-1920 (Box 4)
- "Francis W. Parker School studies in education: The individual and the curriculum", 1920 (Box 4)
- The School Review, Vol. XXVIII, 1920 November (Box 4)
- "Report of the Conference on New Ideals in Education held at Keble College, Oxford", 1923 (Box 4)
- Printed material relating to the Dalton Laboratory Plan, 1924, undated (Box 4)
- Printed material, 1923, undated (Box 4)
- Photographs of students in classrooms, including the Dalton School Art Department, 1920s (Box 4)
- Reproduction of a 1906 photograph of an unidentified woman, possibly Josephine Boardman Crane, undated (Box 4)
- Two portrait photographs of Helen Parkhurst, undated (Box 5)
- Photographs of children performing a play, 1920s (Box 5)
- Scrapbook containing clippings relating to education, 1918 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook containing clippings relating to The Dalton Plan, 1921-1922 (Box 5)